I just released a video on how AI is
going down the path of enshittification.
It'll be linked right up here in the
description if you want to check it out,
but I thought this was going to be a
rather slow process that would take
months or even a year or two to fully go
down the path of raising the prices and
reducing the quantity of what we get,
but it is actually accelerating much
quicker than I thought. GitHub with
Copilot just sent me an email today
essentially saying they're entirely
removing all of the good things related
to that their Copilot plan and making it
essentially on par with just paying for
AI directly. It's honestly embarrassing
seeing the changes that they've made.
Let's take a look at what these changes
entail. Starting on June 1st, they're
essentially removing the entire idea of
premium request units. Essentially what
that meant is that you had a set number
of requests you could make to an AI. It
was 300 with the $10 a month plan, which
is what I was on, and essentially you
could send 300 requests to the AI and
then it'd respond to you and it wouldn't
matter how many tokens were taken. It
would just be based on the request. And
certain models such as like Opus would
consume more than one request while
cheaper models may consume less actual
request. But in generally you got a
certain number of requests you could
make and it didn't matter how many
tokens there were. Obviously this was
consuming tons of money for GitHub and
Copilot, so they decided to completely
scratch that entire idea. They removed
this entirely, and instead now you still
have your $10 and your $39 a month plan,
but instead of getting these requests,
all you do is just get credits that go
towards actually paying for the AI based
on a token based number. And if we look
here, they've also changed it so that
you no longer can use any free models.
There used to be free models included in
the monthly plan that didn't count
against you. Those have all been
removed. And if you're using things like
code review with Copilot that uses
GitHub actions behind the scenes,
they're now going to be charging you for
that as well. So essentially they're
just charging you for absolutely
everything that you used to be getting
for free, which because they don't have
enough money to do this is why they're
doing that, but it essentially removes
all the value you're getting for paying
for this particular service. The only
thing that you're still getting that's
free is the in-editor code complete and
edit suggestions. Otherwise, everything
else is being changed completely. And
the biggest thing that's changing for
someone that's gone the yearly plan,
which is actually what I was on, which
we scroll to that section you can see
anyone that's on the annual plan,
they're not even offering that anymore,
so they're actually completely removing
the annual plan, and they're going to be
changing how the model multipliers work
for your premium requests because they
want to honor that same premium request
situation. I figured they would increase
it slightly, maybe twice as much, three
times as much, but it's honestly
embarrassing looking at what they've
done. If we scroll down to the brand new
chart for these multipliers, you can see
the old multipliers on the left. For
example, you can see here Claude Opus
was at three, while now it's going to be
15 credits. Or if you look at the newer
models of Opus, you can see originally
it was three premium requests, now it's
27. That's a nine times increase, and
this is very consistent. You can see
Sonnet went from one to nine. You can
see down here we're going from one to
six, one to three. There's essentially a
three to nine times increase on almost
every single model that you're being
charged for. And if you're only getting
300 requests per month, that means that
you can essentially make 10 Opus
requests per month on this plan, or you
can make 30 different requests on the
Sonnet. So that's 30 AI requests per
month. That's essentially one per day.
Obviously that's not going to be enough
for doing any type of real world actual
work. And if we look at the actual
pricing that they've changed it to,
essentially you're just paying a per
unit price for the tokens you're using,
and they're just using the exact pricing
model of Claude. So you can see here for
Haiku, it's $1 input, $5 for output. And
if we look here, $1 input, $5 output. So
you're getting no discount, no benefit.
You're just prepaying for these credits
ahead of time, and if you exceed your
prepaid limit, you just pay at the exact
same rate you would pay if you used
Claude directly. So I don't see
absolutely any benefit in using
something like GitHub Copilot anymore
other than that you get the in-editor
code completion. That's the only thing
you're getting by paying this additional
money. And if you're not on their $39 a
month plan, you don't even get access to
these Opus models. They're only
available on the more expensive plan. So
if you want to use these better models,
you have to just pay more upfront and
hope you use that usage limit. Now, most
likely you are going to use that usage
limit because $10 a month or $39 a month
is not a lot when your output tokens are
costing, you know, $15 per million and
so on, but still it's you're pay
prepaying essentially for something that
you're getting at the exact same rate.
It doesn't really make any sense to me,
and I don't really see the benefit of
using something like GitHub Copilot
anymore when you could just pay directly
with Claude, for example, or use one of
Claude's plans that still technically
exist at that time where you can pay
essentially a monthly rate to get a
certain amount of usage out of it.
Eventually, I am guaranteeing you that
this will go away as well, the same way
that Copilot has removed the ability to
do just a one flat fee monthly thing. I
think every single one of these plans is
essentially going to go to the point
where they price you exactly the same as
what the API pricing is, and maybe
people like Claude or OpenAI that have
their own models are going to be able to
offer you a slight discount if you're
using like Claude code or something,
it'll be a small discount, but
realistically, this is the rate that
we're going to be paying going forward,
and it's changing much quicker than I
actually thought it would. And if you
want to learn more about what this
actually means and how this
enshittification is going to actually
affect all of us, I highly recommend
checking out that video that I released
just a few days ago. I will link that
video right over here on your screen,
and it'll be down in the description
below.